Guide to the Manet Harrison Fowler and Manet Helen Fowler Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Manet Harrison Fowler and Manet Helen Fowler papers
1902-1984
JWJ MSS 59
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.88
(9 boxes)
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Manet Harrison Fowler and her daughter Manet Helen Fowler. The Manet Harrison Fowler material documents her work as a singer, musician, and educator with the Mwalimu School and the Texas Association of Negro Musicians. The Manet Helen Fowler material documents her various research and professional activities with the Tarrant County Black Historical and Genealogical Society and other organizations. Material includes photographs; printed material relating to the Mwalimu School and sound recordings of the Mwalimu Festival Chorus; programs for performances by and sound recordings of Manet Harrison Fowler; and original oil paintings by Manet Harrison Fowler. Also included are correspondence, research files, and personal papers of Manet Helen Fowler. The collection provides documentation of African American musicians and music education, particularly African American women musicians and teachers, during and after the Harlem Renaissance.
Fowler, Manet Harrison, 1895-1976
Fowler, Manet Helen, b. 1918
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 5 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Manet Harrison Fowler (1895-1976)
Manet Harrison Fowler was an African American singer, musician, and educator from Fort Worth, Texas. She graduated from the Tuskegee Institute in 1913 and studied at the Chicago College of Music. She co-founded the Texas Association of Negro Musicians and in 1928 founded the Mwalimu School in Texas, later relocating it to Harlem. The school was associated with the Harlem Renaissance, providing educational opportunities in the arts for Harlem's residents. Under the direction of Fowler, the Mwalimu School choir regularly performed and recorded. Fowler was also a painter whose style incorporated religious and civil rights themes.
Manet Harrison Fowler was the wife of Stephen H. Fowler, and the mother of four children: Manet Helen (b. 1918), Stephen Hamilton (b. 1918), George Harrison (b. 1920), and Carroll Lacy (b. 1924).
Manet Helen Fowler (b. 1918)
Manet Helen Fowler was the eldest daughter of Manet Harrison Fowler and Stephen H. Fowler. In 1952, she became the first African American woman to receive a Ph.D. in cultural anthropology from a university in the United States.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Manet Harrison Fowler and her daughter Manet Helen Fowler. The Manet Harrison Fowler material documents her work as a singer, musician, and educator with the Mwalimu School and the Texas Association of Negro Musicians. The Manet Helen Fowler material documents her various research and professional activities with the Tarrant County Black Historical and Genealogical Society and other organizations. Material includes photographs; printed material relating to the Mwalimu School and sound recordings of the Mwalimu Festival Chorus; programs for performances by and sound recordings of Manet Harrison Fowler; and oil paintings by Manet Harrison Fowler. Also included are correspondence, research files, and personal papers of Manet Helen Fowler. The collection provides documentation of African American musicians and music education, particularly African American women musicians and teachers, during and after the Harlem Renaissance.
Arrangement
Arranged into five series: I. Correspondence. II. Photographs. III. Other Papers. IV. Sound Recordings. V. Art Work.
African American music teachers; African American musicians; African American women musicians; African American women teachers; African Americans -- Music; Arts -- Study and teaching; Harlem Renaissance; Music -- New York (State); Audiovisual materials; Oil paintings (visual works); Phonograph records; Photographs; Sound recordings; Music teachers; Musicians; Fowler, Manet Harrison, 1895-1976; Fowler, Manet Helen, b. 1918; Mwalimu Festival Chorus; Mwalimu School (New York, N.Y.); Tarrant County Black Historical and Genealogical Society; Texas Association of Negro Musicians
- Correspondence, Series I
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is largely unsorted within files.
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of the correspondence consists of letters received by Manet Helen Fowler, addressed to Miss Manet Fowler or Dr. Manet Fowler. Also found is some correspondence received by Manet Harrison Fowler and some Fowler family correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1930-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    Includes some correspondence to Manet Harrison Fowler.
  - Correspondence, 1960-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  - Correspondence from Lonnie Jackson, 1939-1943 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence to Manet Harrison Fowler from E. Clyde Whitlock, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence to Manet Harrison Fowler from Mrs. Guy R. Pitner, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Photographs, Series II
  - Harrison and Fowler Family Photographs, circa 1890-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Manet Harrison Fowler Photographs, circa 1913-1950 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mwalimu School Photographs, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
- Other Papers, Series III
  - Manuscript music composed by Manet Harrison Fowler, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Mwalimu School, 1932-1959 (Box 3, Folder 21-23)
  - Texas Association of Negro Musicians, 1930-1956 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Programs, Performances by Manet Harrison Fowler (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Programs, Various Performances (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1930-1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Newsletters and other printed material (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Genealogical and Historical Research and Writing (Box 4, Folder 29-32)
    Some or all of this material is related to Manet Helen Fowler's work as consultant for the Tarrant County Black Historical and Genealogical Society.
  - Scrapbook, Student Memories, Manet Helen Fowler, 1928-1932 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Diploma and certificate, Stephen H. Fowler (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Binder originally housing Mwalimu Festival Chorus phonograph records (Box 6, Folder 48)
- Sound Recordings, Series IV
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 5 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Mwalimu Song," sung by Mwalimu Festival Chorus, phonograph record (Box 5 (Record album storage), Folder 35)
  - "Deep River Thus Saith the Lord," Accomp. by Manet Harrison Fowler, phonograph record (Box 5 (Record album storage), Folder 36)
  - Eva Brown Studio, Manet Fowler on piano, phonograph record, 11 June 1943 (Box 5 (Record album storage), Folder 37)
  - "A Name to Remember," William A. Fowler's Band, phonograph record (Box 5 (Record album storage), Folder 38)
  - Mwalimu Festival Chorus, phonograph records, 31 March 1939 (Box 5 (Record album storage), Folder 39-47)
- Art Work, Series V
  - "De Ole Ship of Zion," original oil painting by Manet Harrison Fowler (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - "Swing Low Sweet Chariot," original oil painting by Manet Harrison Fowler (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - "Git on Board," original oil painting by Manet Harrison Fowler (Box 9, Folder 51)